This is the VOA special English technology report a
Few degrees can make a big difference when it comes to food storage
Foods can go bad if they get too warm
But for many of the world's poor
Finding a good way to keep food cool is difficult
refrigerators are costly and they need electricity
Yet spoiled food not only creates health risks, but also
economic losses
Farmers lose money when they have to throw away products that they cannot sell quickly
but in
1995 a teacher in northern Nigeria named Mohammed Bahaba found a solution
He developed the pot-in-pot
conservation cooling system
It uses two round containers made of clay a smaller pot is placed inside a larger one
The space between the two pots is filled with wet sand
The inner pot can be filled with fruit vegetables or drinks a
Wet cloth covers the whole cooling system
Food stored in the smaller pot is kept from spoiling through a simple
evaporation process
water in the sand between the two pots
evaporates through the surface of the larger pot where drier outside air is moving
The evaporation process creates a drop in temperature of several degrees
This cools the inner pot and helps keep food safe from harmful bacteria
Some foods can be kept fresh this way for several weeks
people throughout Nigeria
began using the invention and
It became popular with farmers in other African countries
Mohammed Bahaba personally
Financed the first
5000 pot-in-pot systems for his own community and five villages
nearby in
2000 the Rolex watch company of Switzerland
Honored him with the Rolex Award for Enterprise
This award recognizes people trying to develop projects aimed at improving human knowledge and
well-being a
committee considers projects in science and medicine
technology
exploration and
discovery the environment and
cultural history
Winners receive a financial assistance to help develop and extend their projects
The awards are given every two years. The next awards will be presented in late
Last year
Rolex launched the Young Laureates program for the younger generation
For VOA special English, I'm Carolyn Pursuti
We have more programs at
VOA special English
calm
where people can read
listen and learn English with texts
MP3's and
activities
We also offer English lessons at the VOA learning English page on
Facebook
From VOA learning English, this is the technology report
High-tech companies are developing the next generation of products that will help us drive cars
do our shopping and
even care for our children the technology company Intel
Recently held a demonstration of some of its new devices in San Francisco
One device measured how alert a driver was
Sensors connected to the driver's head measured brain activity
Cameras placed on the cars dashboard measured eye movement
Justin Ratner
Works at Intel Labs
He says the devices
Measure how much of the brain is occupied while the person is driving
Devices like these he says will make driving safer
Another experimental Intel technology links cars electronically to help prevent crashes
When the driver of the car in front
Signals a turn or slows down an alert message is sent to the car in back
There was also a demonstration of a virtual computer
The computer was projected onto the table from a controller hidden in a flower pot
Sensors read the movements of the user's hands. So there was no need for a mouse or other
handheld device
This technology could be used in everyday situations
At a market
Sensors and computer chips placed in products could help shoppers
Find the items they want to buy
For example, the technology could help them avoid foods that could cause an allergic reaction
Cameras and sensors are already available to help parents watch their children
In the future, other equipment will monitor a baby's health and mood
And security systems are being improved and simplified with face recognition software
Instead of complicated passwords
For VOA Learning